A Finding Aid to the Dotty Attie papers, circa 1950s-2014, in the Archives of American Art AAA.attidott
Archives of American Art
Dotty Attie papers
circa 1950s-2014
AAA.attidott
Archives of American Art
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of New York City painter and printmaker Dotty Attie measure 2.3 linear feet and date from circa 1950s to 2014. Her papers include scattered biographical material, professional files, notes, personal business records, photographs, artwork, and 12 sketchbooks.
Attie, Dotty, 1938-
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1974-circa 2006 (0.1 linear foot; Box 1)
Series 2: Professional Files, circa 1970s-2014 (.9 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Notes, circa 1970s-1990s (.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1982-2013 (.1 linear foot; Box 2)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1960s-1990s (.3 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 6: Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1950s-1970s (.7 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Biographical/Historical note
Dotty Attie, née Laibow (1938- ), is an American painter and printmaker based in New York City who has been exhibiting in museums and galleries since the 1960s. As a co-founder of Artists in Residence (A.I.R.) Gallery, one of the first all-female cooperative galleries in the United States, Attie has had a considerable impact on the art world prejudices against women artists.
Born in Pennsauken, New Jersey, Attie pursued her interest in art at the Philadelphia College of Art, and received her BFA in 1959. In 1962, she married the photographer David Attie and they had two children. Throughout the 1960s, Attie continued her education through fellowships at the Brooklyn Museum of Art School and the Art Students League.
In 1972, Attie and five other women founded A.I.R. Gallery, setting the example of the women's cooperative gallery that would be followed across the country. Attie was a member of A.I.R. Gallery until 1988 and during that time exhibited her own work, curated and co-curated several exhibitions of women artists, organized panels on subjects of interest to women artists, and worked to make the art world more inclusive to women.
Attie gained national and international recognition through her involvement with A.I.R. Gallery and has received numerous fellowships, grants, residencies, as well as exhibitions in galleries and museums nationally and internationally. Attie has also served as faculty at the Cooper Union and Rhode Island School of Design.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2015 by Dotty Attie.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Artist in Residence (A.I.R.) Gallery records.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York City painter and printmaker Dotty Attie measure 2.3 linear feet and date from circa 1950s to 2014. Her papers include scattered biographical material, professional files, notes, personal business records, photographs, artwork, and 12 sketchbooks.
Scattered biographical materials include identification cards, an address book, artist statements and biographies, a few personal letters, and interviews.
Professional files document exhibitions, residencies, and fellowships. Contents of files vary and may include letters and invitations, letters from colleagues and admirers of her work, inventory lists, interviews, loan agreements, travel itineraries, printed materials, photographs, and miscellany. Notes include pages from a notebook that includes both technical instruction and personal notes. There is written text that Attie wrote to be incorporated into her artwork. One file of personal business records contains loan agreements, shipping receipts, and membership fees.
Photographs are of Attie, artwork, and friends and family. Photographs of artwork include exhibition views, single works, and collages. Photographs of Attie include contact sheets and prints of the artist throughout her life, including some copy prints of Attie as a child. Some images of Attie are self-portraits. Photographs of family and friends include her husband, children, A.I.R. Gallery members, and copy prints of relatives.
Artwork and sketchbooks include artists' books, sketches on tracing paper, and 12 sketchbooks.
Interviews; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Printmakers--New York (State)--New York; Sketchbooks; Women artists--New York (State)--New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1974-circa 2006; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material contains identification cards, an address book, artist statements and biographies, interviews, and personal correspondence including letters, postcards, and holiday and greeting cards.
  - General Biographical Materials, 1980-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, circa 1974-circa 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Professional Files, circa 1970s-2014; Series 2; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1
  Professional files document Attie's professional career and opportunities she received for exhibitions, residencies, and fellowships. These files contain letters and invitations from galleries, museums, arts and residency organizations, print shops, publishers, and colleges and universities. Attie also received letters from colleagues and admirers of her work. Also included are inventory lists, interviews, loan agreements, travel details, print documentation, photographs, student rosters, exhibition flyers, newsletters, and articles featuring Attie.
  - A.I.R. Gallery, circa 1970s-2014 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Faculty Files, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Professional Files and Correspondence, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Professional Files and Correspondence, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - General Professional Files and Correspondence, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
  - General Professional Files and Correspondence, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - General Professional Files and Correspondence, circa 2010-2014 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mary Ryan Gallery Exhibition Guest Book (Photocopy), circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - P.P.O.W. Gallery, 1990-2014 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Visiting Artist Panels and Talks, 1977-2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Notes, circa 1970s-1990s; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Notes include pages from notebooks that contain technical instructions and personal notes. Also found in this series is text that Attie wrote to be incorporated into her artwork.
  - General Notes, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Text for Artwork, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
- Personal Business Records, 1982-2013; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include loan agreements with galleries and museums exhibiting Attie's work; receipts documenting artwork shipment, art supplies purchased, and membership fees; and invoices for services provided.
  - Personal Business Records, 1982-2013 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photographs, circa 1960s-1990s; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Photographs are of Attie, friends and family, and artwork. Photographs of artwork include exhibition views, single works, and collages. Photographs of Attie include contact sheets and prints of the artist throughout her life, including some copy prints of Attie as a child. Some images of Attie are self-portraits. Photographs of family and friends include her husband, children, A.I.R. Gallery members, and copy prints of relatives.
  - Artwork, circa 1970s-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dotty Attie, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Family and Friends, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Oversize Artwork from Box 2, Folder 6 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Dotty Attie from Box 2, Folder 7 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Friends and Family from Box 2, Folder 8 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1950s-1970s; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Artwork includes 4 artist's books and preliminary sketches on tracing paper. Sketchbooks (12) contain ink and pencil drawings, primarily of figures and preliminary sketches.
  - Artist's Books, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbooks (4), Dorothy Laibow, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
  - Sketchbooks (2), Dorothy Attie, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbooks (2), circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3)
  - Sketchbook, Dorothy Attie, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
  - Sketchbooks (3), circa 1970s (Box 3)
  - Sketches, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)